so let's talk about blood
donations yeah because on my channel as
you know we've talked a lot uh about
blood donations and most experts that
have been on the channel talking about
high hematocrit and so on we've always
said no no need to donate blood on trt
so now you're saying other things so and
again we're not going to base those
recommendation on the hemoglobin
hematocrite and I've done multiple
podcasts on that subject we've never had
a study a very powerful study that shows
that high hemoglobin hematocrit is
increase increases the risk of blood
clots or heart disease we've never been
able to see a study for this most
studies show that long-term testosterone
is beneficial um the studies that showed
that maybe there's an increase in blood
clots most of those patient had a blood
clotting disorder some kind of
Hemophilia so we've never seen that so
based on the hemoglobin hematocrit
that's not where I'm putting my
recommendations to donate blood it's not
based on the hemoglobin although I'm
going to tell you as somebody on
testosterone and I did experience a
higher hematocrit up to 53 I was
symptomatic I felt a heavy head a little
congested a little more hot flashes and
then when I donated blood it felt better
so I felt the symptoms some people get
their hemat up to 56 58 and they have no
symptoms but I've seen many patients
with high hemat that their blood
pressure is a little higher they
complain of a mild headache or buzzing
sound they get hot flashes more often
they don't feel as well maybe a little
more palpitations so low iron is bad
high iron when you think about the the
the the Dynamics of blood if you have
thicker blood into a fixed vessel you
don't want that you want less viscosity
so I'm not recommending because so far
we haven't had a clear answer and when I
have discussions about this we can say
yes or no if it's harmful we don't know
so high h& so far we haven't had a study
that's power enough to let us know if we
need not to worry or should we worry
right now because we don't know we said
some most studies don't show an
association but there was a study that
was done by Dr um Dr ramasami at
University of Miami and it did it was a
small study and it's I forgot how many
people but it showed that guys who have
high h& the first year after studying
testerone tended to have a poor outcome
cardiovascular wise it was a very small
study and his conclusion said that well
that study points that we need a more
defintive study so right now I'm going
to stay with the same based on level of
hemoglobin and hematocrite level of
secondary Arroyos this is not where I
recommend to donate blood allthough as
per the American of
Endocrinology he hematocrit above 54 was
found to have adverse consequences so
what I do at my practice if you become
if yourid goes above 54 I site the
American Endocrinology Association and I
recommend for my patients to donate and
I'm going to tell you why it's important
to do this as providers because we have
a friend that had a patient that had a
heart attack and a stroke with the
hematocrit being in the 56 and they went
after him because they say the
guidelines in the US show that if imate
of above 54 that you should either
change the dose decrease the dose and
recommend blood donation if you don't do
this the patient has a bad outcome you
cannot be protected so for all the
providers out there although we don't
have full evidence the American
Endocrinology Association has this and
it's a standard of care that it's about
54 and there's a bad outcome you may be
exposed okay now if we're going to talk
now about the ftin level and the reason
for blood donation we have a lot of
evidence I cited the feast study iron in
atherosclerosis study where they
followed 1700 patient for six years and
they showed that phlebotomy reducing the
fertin in the 40 to 80 range um
definitely and it was statistically
significant decreased the end point of
death heart attacks and stroke and the
earlier the better and earlier I mean
those patients were between 43 and 61
strong Association it also showed a
decrease in cancer strong Association if
we look now at the Scandinavian heart
study the Copenhagen heart study you
look at the level of f in less than 200
associated with a higher range a higher
mean survival um death if we look now
there's other studies that show that
frequent blood donors and frequent blood
donors are two to three times a year
live on average longer than non-life
non-blood donors and I have all of those
studies again Stephen I told you I'm
going to create an iron class where I'm
going to be able to get all of this for
any patient who's Ed with all the
citations and really keep talking about
this so blood donation is important and
if we think about our medical history
we've always done some kind of blood
donation blood leing uh in the Middle
Ages the way doctors treat patients was
by Venus section they cut your veins let
you bleed out in the Victorian era in
the 1800 we've used leeches in Paris
there were hospitals all they did was
leeches therapy people had their own
leeches because the said it remove bad
blood B Moes hum um all kinds of things
at the end of the day what we realize it
was removing
iron yeah so blood donation multiple
studies I'm going to say there's a few
studies theyve done a couple of
randomized control trials to compare end
points and there are some studies that
show that there were no benefits to
blood donation no harm also but it just
said ah we don't see any positive but we
have those studies the Fe study the
Copenhagen study you can go and look at
those things and you see that there are
a lot of data to support this and then
blood donation is something good every
time me and my wife go and donate blood
I feel good the whole week because I
feel like I've done something so it's
funny in my iron presentation I have a
nice email that they sent to my wife
after she donated blood and they said
the email came that uh your blood
matched with a child at whatever
Hospital your blood is on its way to
save his
life makes you feel good it's a selfless
act that's actually good for you you
know every two seconds in the US
somebody needs blood we're short in
blood so you do something good for
somebody and you also dump iron that's
good for your
health